Finding Aid for Charles M. Ziegler papers, 1928-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles M. Ziegler papers 1928-1959
Ziegler, Charles M., 1888-1959.
86436 Aa 2; AC; Ac
Republican State Highway Commissioner, 1943-1957. Correspondence, scrapbooks and other papers concerning the highway department, Republican politics, and his interest in the Michigan Republican League, the Michigan Indian Foundation, and the construction of the Mackinac Bridge; also photographs.
2 linear feet
9 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Charles M. Ziegler (donor no. 3534 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles M. Ziegler was born on a farm in Noble County, Indiana, May 23, 1888. A graduate of Saginaw Eastern High School in 1908, he received his Bachelor of Science degree in Civil Engineering at the University of Michigan in 1913.
His professional career in engineering began with the Saginaw Engineering Department as an assistant city engineer in 1918. From 1918 to 1919, he worked for the United States Government in airplane work at McCook Field, Dayton, Ohio; in 1919 he became assistant division engineer with the Michigan State Highway Department and became Deputy Highway Commissioner and served for several years before leaving the department in 1933.
He was engaged in various engineering activities from 1933 until elected Lansing City Assessor in 1938; he was re-elected in 1940 and served in that capacity until elected State Highway Commissioner on the Republican ticket in 1943. He took office on April 20, 1943, to fill an unexpired term and was re-elected in 1945, 1949 and 1953. Ziegler did not stand for reelection in 1957. Charles M. Ziegler died in 1959.
The collections includes the following series of papers: Correspondence; Campaign and Republican Party Activities; Michigan Highway Department; Topical files and miscellaneous; and Scrapbooks and clippings. Much of the correspondence relates to his first campaign in 1943 for Highway Commissioner.
Subjects:
Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Ingham County (Mich.). Emergency Welfare Relief Commission.; Michigan Indian Foundation.; Mackinac Bridge Authority (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan Republican League.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Public welfare--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Roads--Michigan.; Ziegler, Charles M., 1888-1959.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automobiles--1941-1950.; Carriages and coaches.; Ferries.; Grand Hotel (Mackinac Island, Mich.); Hotels and taverns--Michigan--Mackinac Island.; Launchings.; Mackinaw City (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.)--Hotels and taverns.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Newaygo (Mich.); Piers and wharves--Michigan--Saint Ignace.; Saint Ignace (Mich.)--Piers and wharves.; Vacationland (Ferry); Ziegler, Charles M., 1888-1959.; Ziegler family.
Contributors:
Bennett, John B. (John Bonifas), 1905-1964.; Blackney, William Wallace, 1876-1963.; Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.; Dillman, Grover C. (Grover Cleveland), 1889-1979; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - 1928-1942 (Box 1)
    (include letters from Grover Dillman, July 2, 1930 and 1941, from Frank D. McKay, June 8, 1942, also letter from Fred L. Crawford, 1942)
  - 1943
    (include letters from John B. Bennett, Grover Dillman, and William Blackney)
    - January 1943 (Box 1)
      (include letter from Fred L. Crawford, January 27, 1943)
    - February 1-15, 1943 (Box 1)
    - February 16-23, 1943 (Box 1)
    - February 24-28, 1943 (Box 1)
    - March 1943 (Box 1)
    - April-December 1943 (Box 1)
      (include letter from Earl C. Michener, April 8, 1943)
  - 1944-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 1)
    (include letter from Frank D. McKay, December 25, 1955)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    (include letter from G. Mennen Williams, 1957)
  - 1956-1957 with Richard H. Fletcher (Box 1)
- Campaign and Republican Party Activities
  - Michigan Republican League 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Ziegler's election campaign 1953 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning politics 1937-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - List of delegates to the Republican State Convention
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
- Michigan Highway Department
  - General
    - 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Speeches undated (Box 2)
  - Mackinac Bridge Authority 1951-1957 (Box 2)
  - Road Construction report 1957 (Box 2)
  - Bridge Construction report 1957 (Box 2)
  - Notebook concerning law suit against the Highway Department 1947 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Topical files and miscellaneous
  - Ingham County Emergency Welfare Relief Commission bulletins 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Indian Foundation, Inc. 1950-1956 (Box 2)
  - Rotary Club 1943-1953 (Box 2)
  - Other organizational membership 1943-1957 (Box 2)
  - Notebook containing lists of names of officeholders and officials of organizations 1957 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous topics 1943-1957, 5 folders (Box 2)
    (include citations and resolutions of appreciation)
    (see also oversize folder Ac)
  - Photographs: Portraits; photographs of Ziegler, his wife, and daughter at launching ceremonies of car ferry, Vacationland, on April 7, 1951; photos of various earlier car ferries and of the boarding docks and warehouse at Saint Ignace, Michigan; and photographs of other Highway Department staff and activities, 2 envelopes (Box 2)
  - Student Notebooks 1910-1914, undated, 5 volumes (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks and clippings
  - Newspaper clippings 1935-1949 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings 1955-1957 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1943-1944 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook 1945-1948 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook 1948-1949 (Volume 3)
  - Scrapbook 1950-1952 (Volume 4)
  - Scrapbook 1953 (Volume 5)
  - Scrapbook 1954-1955 (Volume 6)
  - Scrapbook 1955-1957 (Volume 7)
  - Scrapbook (election campaign) 1937 election (Volume 8)
  - Scrapbook (election campaign) 1943 (Volume 9)